We now have footage of the post-mortem
human brain slice learning to play the
piano. Yes, you are watching a piece of
brain from someone who used to be a
person that's been hooked up to a robot
and has learned to play the piano by
listening. This research was published
by French researchers back in May and is
a little bit more than morbid, but there
is good reason why you would want to do
this and there is a whole lot of ethical
consideration as you may have guessed.
Now your first question might be is this
going to go commercial? And no, probably
not. We don't really have a whole lot of
uses for adult brains when it comes to
robots or computation. We do have a lot
of uses for just lab-grown human brains
or brain organoids. There's whole data
centers that have been set up on those
guys.
But for an adult brain, they've already
largely lived a life and they've also
grown around being part of a brain and a
body. So they're just not all that
effective.
No, this is extraordinarily useful for
research if you think about it. A lot of
our research is done on stem cells and
those are very very young in age. They
are a representation for a person, but
they're essentially a very very young
person. Our alternatives are growing
human stem cells in mice and that has
its own ethical concerns, but it's also
still, you know, a mouse.
If we take pieces of brain from adults,
that represents an adult that has lived
their life and you aren't just giving
them a condition, they had that
condition. So they're really a very good
research subject. Even more so if
they're operating a robot, we can study
sensory motor learning. This kind of
research has and will continue to bring
us treatments. This is the first line
before we ever get to animal trials or
human trials. So really, it probably is
ethical overall. Now let's talk about
the experiment because we have known for
a long time that you can take human
brain tissue, brain slices, and keep it
alive outside of the body for even
weeks. You just have to give it oxygen
and glucose and things to eat and you
have to keep bacteria from infecting it.
Researchers have known that they
continue to have electrical activity,
again, for weeks. Pretty much for as
long as the brain tissue is alive and
no, it's not exactly the same as you
might think of in an adult human brain.
There's not signs of consciousness going
on, at least not the same brain waves
that we would associate with it, but you
can run tests and see how medication
might impact brain activity.
Minor brain activity, the little bit of
brain activity that is present. What had
not been demonstrated up until now is
that that brain is capable of learning
things and you can set it up with
sensory motor experience of sorts. Yes,
they did set up a microphone and hooked
that up to the brain so it could get
feedback and was meaningful and it had
to learn how to play the piano first
using motor babbling.
Meaning it just did things randomly
until it got it right and then it would
get a little electrical impulse
demonstrating that it got it correctly.
And our brains are wired to learn, they
are essentially physical reservoir
computers of sorts, they're just, you
know, squishy chemical ones.
I know, I know it all sounds a little
bit morbid, but when we are talking
about individual neurons, each
individual is not conscious, even a
cluster of them is not conscious as far
as we know. You know, that's not
actually all that fair to say because we
don't really know what consciousness is.
It's just not equivalent to the
experience of an entire brain, probably.
The part of me that is a scientist is
having a really hard time with the part
of me that doesn't want people to
misunderstand this experiment and that
is tough because you got to hedge.
There's a lot of things we don't know
for certain, actually we don't know
anything for certain.
Now early on you can see that the robot
hand is playing music essentially
randomly. You can see a human
participant, so the researchers are
demonstrating how to play the piano to
the robot hand.
Then they did something different. They
gave it Tania virus and I cannot say
that word correctly. However, the brain
lost its ability to play once it was
made ill. Now this is not terribly
dangerous to people, it causes flu-like
symptoms, but you can watch the brain
failing to know how to play.
And it's probably good that I don't
actually work in technomancy because I
clearly anthropomorphize the brain
slice, but I feel bad for it.
Now, research like this is progressing
rapidly and we probably need to approach
as a society how we want to deal with it
ethically because until now and really
still now, brain tissue is treated the
same as any other kind of tissue in an
experiment. We never really thought that
you'd be able to revive human brains in
any capacity, let alone teach them to
operate a robot hand that plays piano.
And yes, researchers are considering the
ethics of it and they are publishing
prospective papers on it, but the
technology is moving a lot faster than
our ability to regulate it. So, we just
have to hope that everyone has goodwill
and I for one I'm just kind of excited
when I see papers like this. They're
They're just very cool. It's a part of
me that loves sci-fi and maybe the part
of me that loves horror.
I do hope you've enjoyed this. I will
keep you up to date. In fact, you have
no choice. Follow for more.